The world of Pandora will change forever.
Avatar: Fire and Ash is a science fiction, adventure,
fantasy film directed by James Cameron.
In the wake of the devastating war against the RDA and the loss of their eldest son, Jake Sully and Neytiri face a new
threat on Pandora: the Ash People, a violent and power-hungry Na'vi tribe led by the ruthless Varang.
Jake's family must fight for their survival and the future of Pandora in a
conflict that pushes them to their emotional and physical limits.
Jake, played by Sam Worthington.
Neytiri, played by Zoe Saldaña.
Kiri, played by Sigourney Weaver.
Quaritch, played by Stephen Lang.
Varang, played by Oona Chaplin.
Spider, played by Jack Champion.
Avatar: Fire and Ash is a 2025 American epic science fiction film directed by
James Cameron, and written by Cameron, Rick Jaffa and Amanda Silver.
It is the third in the Avatar film series, and features Sam Worthington, Zoe Saldaña, Sigourney Weaver, Stephen Lang
and Kate Winslet reprising their roles from the previous films, with Oona Chaplin joining the cast.
It follows the human-turned-Na'vi Jake Sully and his family on the habitable moon Pandora, as they face the combined
threat of the human RDA forces and the Mangkwan, a tribe of ruthless, warmongering, collaborationist Na'vi.
Cameron, who had stated in mid-2006 that he would like to make sequels to Avatar (2009) if it was successful, announced the first
two sequels in early 2010 following the success of the first film, with Avatar 3 aiming for a December 2015 release.
However, the addition of two further sequels, and the development of new technology required to film performance capture scenes underwater, a feat never
accomplished before, led to significant delays to allow the crew more time to work on the writing, pre-production, and visual effects.
The film started shooting simultaneously with Avatar: The Way
of Water in New Zealand on September 25, 2017.
Filming completed in late December 2020, after over three years of shooting.
With an estimated production budget of at least $350 million, it
is one of the most expensive films ever made.
Avatar: Fire and Ash had its world premiere at Dolby Theatre in Hollywood, on December 1, 2025,
and was released in the United States on December 19 by 20th Century Studios.
Critical response was generally positive, with praise for the visual effects and
spectacle, but complaints that it repeats the narrative beats of its predecessors.
It grossed $1.379 billion worldwide, becoming the
third-highest grossing film of 2025.
Named among the top ten films of 2025 by the American Film Institute and the National Board of Review, it received two Academy Award (Best Visual Effects and Best Costume Design) and
two Golden Globe Award nominations, and has two planned sequels, Avatar 4 and Avatar 5, production of which is dependent on the box-office performance of Fire and Ash.
The film explores themes of witch, clone, space war, tribe, sequel.
The tone is dark and thought_provoking and emotional.